[Music]
especially in the the interview was
Camille Paglia I think you said that you
fear that the that men checking out
could be a fatal situation for Western
culture gods definitely fatal for
Western culture one of the things that
struck me over the last year all even
last night at the lecture at last
night's lecture 85% of the people were
men now in the twelve part series that
preceded that more and more women came
and then there was this gap but like the
vast majority of the audience was men
and men of all sorts like it wasn't
you're like every sort of man was
represented there young old rough
civilized the whole range you know and
there and they're coming from quite a
long distance many of them you know they
come up and say why I drove from New
York City or I drove from Michigan it's
like well you could watch it on YouTube
it's like no they're not doing that and
that's very promising to me because well
this logos that the West will die
without the rebirth of the logos because
the West is that so
without gone it's gone and we've seen
what's arisen to replace it while
there's fascism
there's communism and then there's the
New Age mess because it's a mess and
most of its wish fulfillment and fantasy
and inability to there's creativity in
it but there's no capacity to edit
whatsoever
there's no coherence and so that's stuff
so weak that anyone with any commitment
can just push it aside and there's no
justification for the for the Marxism
and or for the fascism it's like we
already had that experiment could you
describe what you mean by the rebirth of
the logos then in that context well it's
it's the it's part of it is taking
taking voluntary responsibility for the
appalling conditions of your life
essentially that you're a suffering
creature that's mortal right and that
you're the locus of evil both of the
those things and that it's your response
that your life is about responsibility
and it's your responsibility to
voluntarily accept that and then to do
what you can about it even though it's
in some sense you know it's an
enterprise doomed to failure in some
sense because you're going to die and
and and the world is a carnage a place
of carnage but that that you can accept
that and if you can't accept it then
what that means is that you're not
integrated enough because if your
integrated enough then you can accept it
it's it's like the test of the
integration so your your character isn't
forged sufficiently if you cannot
tolerate that and it's not like it's an
easy thing to tolerate often what people
do is they just don't think about it
they just push it out of their mind and
no wonder but they pay for that with
shallowness and with self contempt and
with with the inability to bear
suffering nobly let's say and that's
there's nothing in that that's good for
people so the rebirth of the logos as
far as I'm concerned is well it's this
willingness to take responsibility to
for the shaping of destiny that's it I
mean the old Mesopotamian God Marduk
when he became the pinnacle God by
election basically one of his demands
from the other gods was that he be in
control of the tablet of destiny right
and so there's an the old idea among the
Mesopotamians was that the highest God
was he who was in control of destiny
it's like well to the degree that you
align yourself properly then you take
responsibility for destiny and that's
that's a concentric set of circles with
no end you know because you can
straighten up yourself and then you can
straighten up your family and if you do
that property you're simultaneously
strengthening
community and and and and then you're a
model for your peers and so that starts
to spread and we don't have any idea
what we would be like if we all got our
acts together like we're pretty amazing
as it is human beings and you know we're
probably devoting who knows what it is
in terms of percentage I mean the doubt
a Ching suggests you know that thirty
percent thirty percent of people are
working to make things better and thirty
percent of people are neutral and thirty
percent are trying to make things worse
so it's obviously a metaphor but but
there's some truth in it we don't know
what it would be like what we would be
like if we put our effort to making
things better devoted our effort to
making things better wherever we went
and it would be interesting to find out
how would you summarize why men are in
crisis no I think it's because in a deep
level the West has lost faith in the
idea of masculinity now that's no
different than the death of God it's the
same thing and so a Nietzsche knew what
the consequence of that would be I mean
that's most of what he wrote about you
know and so you'd say well the divine
symbol of masculinity has been
obliterated well so then what do you
expect what it what's gonna happen it's
gonna that means masculinity is going to
become weak and especially if the symbol
is also denigrated right which it
definitely is so what that means is that
the ideal that man could aspire to is
denigrated and well then with your ideal
in tatters
you're weak that's that's definitional
so I think the reason that men have been
responding positively to my my thinking
let's say is that I don't buy any of
that I like the masculine spirit it's
necessary and it's not fundamentally
carnage and pillaging it's not
fundamentally rape culture you know it
not fundamentally world destroying and
all of those things have been all of
those aspersions have been cast upon it
that's partly the guilt of Western
society for technological progress even
and those are reasonable challenges to
be set before men but they're not
reasonable accusations to swallow
without criticism and and it's not that
what is it what what is the masculinity
we can aspire to well it's a
responsibility fundamentally and it's
it's it's to put it symbolically is that
your your responsibility is to incarnate
the Spirit of the logos that's your
responsibility that's your role in life
and that is independent to some degree
in whether or not you accept the idea of
a transcendent and eternal reality now
I'm not making a case for that or
against that I those things are beyond
human understanding but we know what
happens if people act poorly if men act
badly we know what happens we know that
the world turns into something that's so
close to hell that the difference is
trivial we know that that's the story of
the 20th century so we should learn that
lesson and what that lesson is is pick
up the world on your shoulders and walk
forward
pick up the world with all of its
trouble with all of its suffering with
all of its evil and move forward with it
and in bearing that burden learn that
you're the sort of creature that can
bear that burden and therefore deserving
of respect that's that's the that's
identification with the logos and that's
I don't I've never encountered an idea
that's better than that because it's not
it's so not naive it's the opposite of
naive it's like there's terrible evil
and there's terrible suffering it
bottomless but the human spirit is
capable of voluntarily taking that on as
a challenge well it's worth a try yes
exactly that's that's that's that's the
positive meaning that's the positive
meaning that's the world affirming
meaning you know and that that's that
self-esteem let's say you know which is
very poorly characterized it's very
shallowly characterized because it
usually doesn't involve any sense of
responsibility but you know it's obvious
if you it's obvious in some ways if you
look at the people that other people
spontaneously respect unless they've
become unbelievably cynical it's the
people who adopt responsibility and deal
with it competently so it's not a
mystery that that would be what you
could aspire to now it gets undermined
if you feel that that force of
responsibility is the the raping and
pillaging patriarchal culture that's
despoiling the natural environment and
that's equivalent to a cancer well you
know no I don't buy that and I've seen
that you're skeptical of the idea of the
description of gender as a spectrum but
no I'm suspicious of the motives for for
putting that idea forward and and I also
think it's it's it's an imprecise
definition it's not a spectrum because a
spectrum is equally represented at each
point in the distribution so that's
wrong and it and the it's wrong in the
way that you would expect it to be wrong
given its ideological basis now you know
there's male and female and masculine
and feminine are not exactly the same
thing and so and that's a reasonable
claim and you could also make a case
that
much masculinity without an admixture of
femininity is a form of excess and that
too much femininity without an admixture
of masculinity is an ex is an is an
excess you know or is a is a is a
failure it's it's it's it's an extreme
but the obliteration of the distinction
between male and female or masculine and
feminine is a it's a psychological
catastrophe not least because those are
arguably the most basic cognitive axioms
they're deeper than that there there are
axioms on which our entire cognitive
structures is predicated and yin-yang
yes exactly exactly exactly well and I
think that that's a consequence of our
biological heritage like the reality of
sex sex is very very very old it's a
fundamental issue and sex is
fundamentally about female and male and
there's no getting around that now as I
said you can distinguish masculine and
feminine from that and you can speak
about the psychological components of
sex as well as the physiological
components but the real radicals deny
the physiological components it's like
that's okay
except when they force other people to
do the same kind of denial like people
are entitled to their opinion but
they're not entitled to put it in the
law and so that's why I was opposed to
not to transgender rights or to
transgender people or I mean it's that's
a sideshow in in many ways I'm not
trying to trivialize it but it's not
like a it's not the main event its
emblematic of something else otherwise
no one would have cared and I just see
it as fundamentally oriented towards
destabilization and destruction I think
my I'm just sort of complete that that
question because I think it speaks to
what you just said because I think some
people who are who are not motivated by
the same things that are motivating the
sort of extreme post modernists are some
help us
weighted by their by their claims that
gender is a spectrum because there is
something in as Jung talked about the
anima animus there is something about
the inner masculine the inner feminine
in all of us and there is a complexity
there that that is more than just a sort
of a straightforward masculine face
binary which is where I think that we
might be able to to get out of this now
that's a reasonable point you know I you
know one way of conceptualizing that is
in in terms of let's say in terms of the
archetypes well we use the Christian
archetypes for for illustration so you
could say well for the male generally
speaking the logos is the primary image
and so that would be partly associated
with the word that creates order out of
chaos and also with the sacrificial
crucifixion and that sort of thing the
voluntary acceptance of suffering but
the divine mother and child is behind
that because human males are actually
quite maternal right we we do
participate in raising children even if
they're not our own like you're much
more likely to be abused by a step
farther I think the risk is a hundred
times greater so it's not trivial but
still the fact that it happens at all is
is a biological miracle so human being
males are very maternal for male mammals
or for males period and then females are
pretty masculine I mean but you can kind
of see that the the difference to which
the sexes differ by looking out there
the difference in their in their
physiological configuration you know men
are bigger and stronger than women and
not a tremendous amount although upper
body strength there's a tremendous
difference but that's approximately how
different they are and that's they're
more the same than they are different
but the differences aren't trivial and
the thing is is that differences that
are small at the average can be huge at
the extremes so you might say well if
you took the most agreeable people say
the most comparison
people out of a hundred and segregated
them they would all be women all of them
and if you took the least agreeable
people and those would often be people
who have a criminal bent they would all
be men and often the cultural force is
driven by the extremes not by the middle
and so you don't need huge differences
in the average to produce relatively
large differences in in in cultural
manifestation that's why there are so
many men in prison compared to women you
know that's that's a big deal
and it's not the sexism of society that
does that although it might be to some
degree because like male judges give
female criminals lighter sentences for
example then female judges give female
criminals so but no one ever talks about
that so so yes it's it's reasonable to
note the psychological components of
masculine and feminine let's say it at a
psychological and symbolic level but to
do that at the same time that you're
denying biological reality and playing
an anti patriarchal game behind the
scenes and perhaps masking your Marxist
anti capitalism at the same time it's
contaminates all of it so badly that you
can't have a reasonable discussion and
so even this the transgender issue that
arose in Canada is so contaminated by
the underlying ideology well first of
all people would have just ignored it if
that wasn't the case but it's so
contaminated by the underlying ideology
that you can't trust the legislation not
a bit so and that was my point you can
have a quality but then difference is
also essential within that yeah unless
you want sterile uniformity which is
something that only a tyrant wants I
mean that's what the tyrant wants a
sterile uniformity and and the sterile
is not only ideon 'el sterility but
actual physiological sterility no and
that's no recipe for for the
continuation of a culture you know and
you can be cynical about that and say
well you know one cultures as good as
the next and
no you don't have any responsibility to
continue your culture but it depends on
how you want to construe your life you
know I mean one of the things that's so
interesting about the biblical stories
is that they're these ancient people had
a sense of the continuity of life across
generations that we really don't have
and maybe that's a consequence of I
don't know a too narrow individualism
something like that or or maybe a - or
maybe it's a present centered hedonism
but they're always acting under guidance
from God let's say as if the
consequences of their personal actions
echo down the centuries
you know indefinitely which they
actually do you know and so and then
with regards to the issue of what so you
need men and women to play the role in
that and they have to play their
masculine and feminine roles
fundamentally even though male and
female and masculine feminine are not
exactly the same idea there's there's a
there's no reason to not have the
differentiation it should be it should
be encouraged differentiation I feel
like there's so much in the maps of
meaning and the biblical lectures that I
really want to integrate into what we're
teaching because I think it's so it's
essential stuff mm-hmm for orienting
yourself in the world is it just seems
to be great without it that's right
absolutely
you're you're adrift without it you have
to you have to have a conscious
relationship with the archetypes there's
no way if you don't then you're
susceptible to possession that's
basically or - or to despair yeah so and
no wonder well you've got to have axioms
so the run yeah seems are the archetypes
yes that's where they exist you see a
certain axis biological structures there
at least that yeah they're preexisting
their pre-existing categories of
perception in the Kantian sense that's a
good way of thinking about it is that
you know that the peer empiricist thinks
that you get all your information from
the outside world right but that's not
true because you bring on a priori
interpretive framework
to the world and that's instantiated
biologically but then it's also
enculturated so separating the archetype
from the underlying biological reality
isn't easy so you have the snake you
have the propensity to to perceive
reptilian predators the manner in which
those things are represented in the
culture fill those holes essentially and
so that can same as the language
instinct so yeah that's right exactly
it's the same thing it's the same thing
like the archetypes are manifestations
of the universal grammar grammar of
emotion and motivation that's a good way
of thinking about it now they may be
more than that but because well we you
know I mean life has been moving forward
for 3 and 1/2 billion years and it moves
forward in these pattered and manners
like the dominance hierarchy for example
so that's that let's call that the
masculine archetype it's part of the
masculine archetype in fact the onus
Proclamation was that the female
representation of the male so that's the
animus is the dominance hierarchy it's
the patriarchy so that's that that's the
unconscious archetype which i think is
extremely interesting given what's
happened say in the women's movement
because that's what's projected onto men
and and it can be projected in a very
negative way it doesn't have to be but
it can be and so an animus possessed
woman treats a man as if he's the
manifestation of the tyrannical
patriarchy
he's a group he's that group of men yeah
the group of bad men naturally he spoke
really well about in connecting the
logos and I found often sharing for
example men 'z groups speaking my truth
speaking honestly being vulnerable being
open being available has been really
important I don't hear you talking so
much about the value of say
vulnerability or the value of emotional
honesty is that but as a psyche as a
psychologist that must be something the
well it's more just the value of honesty
in general like you need to say the
things that are you're trying to
represent being as accurately as you can
in your communication right that's part
of the logos process that's the truth
its truth oriented to love I think is
the right formula and love is something
like the desire for being to flourish
rather than to be eradicated right those
are the archetypal realities are you
working for the flourishing of being or
for its eradication and there's a
credible case to be made for its
eradication so but love I think is in
the in the archetypal sense is the
desire for being to flourish and then
truth is truth is the attempt to
represent your relationship with being
in the most precise and accurate manner
possible because well you have to adapt
to reality so you can't adapt to
something too whose existence you will
not admit and so emotional honesty is
part of that but I don't think it's more
important than any of the other elements
of honesty the vulnerability issue is
your modeling not so much your
vulnerability but you're voluntarily
voluntary acceptance of that
vulnerability so because to just model
your vulnerability is not necessarily
distinguishable from being a victim you
know I'm hurt and and I'm saying that
I'm hurt it's that isn't that's not
that's not the whole story the whole
story is well we're all hurt and some of
us more than others certainly but that
it's possible to come to terms with that
and with God's grace let's say and maybe
some help from other people to accept
that and then transcend it and that's
the hope the hope is that you get beyond
your
you're hurt because otherwise you tend
to distribute it and and pay it forward
and and that's not good obviously what
you're asked you to to group work or to
sort of some of the psychological
processing stuff that has come out of
say the 60s and 70s I found it very very
useful that I've not heard you speak
well it can go terribly wrong you know
and that's part of the reason it did in
some ways died out in in the 60s like it
could go terribly wrong the encounter
groups are often very hard on people it
can easily become tyrannical and
totalitarian and I've seen that happen
very rapidly in in group situations but
I mean group work it's part of the way
that you integrate yourself into the
society so it's necessary it's obvious
that group work would be prone to all
those potential catastrophes because
those are the catastrophes of groups but
it's necessary and I would say the
lectures that I'm doing for example
there's group work there because there's
an audience right a crowd and people
like the live part of it and there is a
difference between speaking to people
live in a group and speaking to them say
through electronic means there's a
there's a there's a collective spirit
let's say that manifests itself in the
room and that's a consequence of
everyone imitating everyone else
unconsciously and and so and that that's
a very powerful thing and can also be
provide direction because maybe if
you're fortunate and things are coming
together properly in the room it's the
best part of the crowd that rises up and
then that rises up as a kind of ideal
and then that sort of possesses each
individual because they can see that
they're supported in their journey
forward and that these things can be and
they can look around and think well
these other people are taking this
seriously and paying attention and so
there's something to take serious here
seriously here and to pay attention to
and so that's all good but you have to
be very aware that of the pitfalls and
and so you have to beat yourself with a
stick so that you mean you retain the
proper humility and the humility ideas
are very
complicated one and I think what that is
in essence is that you have to remember
all the time that what you don't know is
more important than what you know you
have to remember that as if your life
depends on it because it does I mean
even technically because there's so much
you don't know you don't know enough
like you're prone to catastrophe so you
don't know enough by definition and if
you know that and understand that then
that can reduce the temptation to to act
in a manner that would be totalitarian
or tyrannical and that can facilitate
the group work you know so it's risky
but everything's risky and just coming
back to the idea of the rebirth of the
logos something's been coming up quite a
lot recently as the idea of initiation
and I there's a couple of organizations
in the UK one called Band of Brothers
which is using men's work initiation
work of some description to take
disadvantaged youths and to give them a
sense of direction give them a sense of
purpose give them a sense of dignity
well part of that's part of what an
initiation is for like part of it is
exposure to that which terrifies you
that's part of it but then in the state
that that produces you're supposed to be
inculcated with the cultural wisdom and
that partly is direction I mean that's
what older men have to provide it's even
the case with elephants you know the the
young elephants herd has been decimated
and the old guys are gone the young guys
basically go insane they're
uncontrollable and obviously that's the
case with human beings and so the the
purpose of mature men or the
responsibility of mature men is to give
young men is to be models obviously but
mostly models of direction yeah well you
need direction you uni and you need
there has to be a rationale for aiming
up because that's direction you don't
aim down that's just why would you aim
down unless you were angry and bitter
and resentful and you know full of
hatred and all that you aim up and and
but that has to be put forward in a way
that isn't this too tight corset
grandmotherly moralizing
because anybody with any sense who isn't
overly domesticated is just gonna reject
that so you know that's the kind of
morality that Nietzsche described his
cowardice right he said most people's
morality is cowardice it's it's they're
afraid they're afraid to be bad and
because they're afraid they think
they're good but they're not good
they're just afraid and that's not
morality morality is a whole different
issue and it's partly aiming up but it's
also partly gathering your forces
together so that you aren't interfered
with well you're moving upward so
because you you will be people test it
do you think the central problem of
Western societies that were intent on
slamming off responsibility at every
level any society where people are
shying away from responsibility is is a
society that's self crippling because
the responsibility is to do the work
that's necessary to revitalize and the
culture to rescue it's it's fundamental
axioms from the darkness to revitalize
it and to have it expand and grow and if
that isn't happening then anything that
isn't growing dies you know that that's
sort of a fundamental truth of life and
so so I don't know if it's precisely the
central problem of the West because it's
not like there aren't people who aren't
taking responsibility in the rest of the
world but it's enough of a problem in
the West that it threatens us and I
think that's particularly felt by young
men I think the reason for that in part
is that there's the direction for young
women in some sense is more obvious both
culturally and biologically because
young women are encouraged if they're
attempting to manifest the logos let's
say they're definitely encouraged in
that there's no doubt about it and then
as a backup they have the divine mother
and child and so they're kind of set
with men it's more this is perhaps why
men
have always undergone a ritual
initiation because they need to be
directed more in a more art in a more
articulate manner in a more conscious
manner they have to be inculcated with
the culture in order to decide that
adopting responsibility is the
appropriate thing to do and they need a
rationale for that because why the hell
would you adopt responsibility without a
rationale it's way like the default
position is aimless impulsive
pleasure-seeking and inertia because all
you have to do to have that is do
nothing and that's easy so then the
question immediate question is well why
not just do that
and what one of the answers is because
you and the world will go to hell and
very rapidly and that's a pretty good
answer and it's actually true now you
know what that means in any eternal
sense is not an easy thing to say but
the proximal sense is true enough so
even in action is not morally acceptable
in the face of the unkempt unfinished
state of being I guess that's a
reasonable way of thinking about
for our full-length documentary on
Jordan Peterson and more great content
check the rebel wisdom website where
you'll also find details of some of the
events we're running for men to give a
direct experience of some of what Jordan
Peterson is talking about
[Music]